Hey,
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): everybody. So, I have a fairly significant guest. Alan Dershowitz probably needs not much of an introduction. Professor Emeritus at Harvard Law, long-standing legal commentator, and I asked him to come on to discuss Robert Mueller's statement on Wednesday, which was obviously designed to instigate impeachment.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): So, we discussed a variety of legal issues related to that, and he initially said that he had 20 minutes to do the podcast, and I managed to extend it to around 38. So, no, did
not get
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): to ask him about every issue under the sun.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): But he said he'd be willing to come back on at a later time And we can revisit various subjects I don't agree with him on many things And I stated as such over the course of this discussion And I probed him on different matters as well
Speaker 2: So listen for yourself, I suppose And here we go
Music
All
Speaker 3: right, Alan Dershowitz, thank you for doing this. My
Speaker 4: pleasure. So
Robert Mueller
Speaker 3: came out with a statement
Speaker 5: yesterday that you reacted quite strongly to in a column in The Hill. And I want to get to that. But quickly first, if
you look at the
Speaker 5: bestselling books in America right now, at least nonfiction books, one of them is a copy of The Mueller Report to which you provided an introduction.
Speaker 5: And I have to admit, I find it a little odd because the Mueller Report is a publicly available document. Anybody
with
Speaker 6: an internet connection can access it. And yes, yet these books are selling like hotcakes.
Speaker 7: How do you interpret that? I was surprised also. I mean, I wrote an introduction.
Speaker 8: Obviously, I have a point of view, and I have a group of people who support my point of view.
Speaker 9: If
you go on
Speaker 9: Amazon, the reviews of my book are either one star of the worst or five stars the best, almost nothing in the middle.
Speaker 10: because most people haven't even read my introduction. They either like me or what I've said up to now and give me five stars, or they hate me in what I've said up to now and
Speaker 8: they give me one star. So I think buying these Mueller reports is a way of voting. If you are voting against the Mueller report, you buy my book. If you're voting in favor of the Mueller report, you buy the Washington Post. And so I doubt very many people who have bought
Speaker 11: these books have actually read the report from beginning.
Speaker 11: to end. I think they've read the introductions, but I doubt very many people have read the 400 and some odd pages, some of which are quite tedious. But it's an important historical record. It doesn't justify the appointment of a special counsel. Special counsel are not supposed to be there for history. They're supposed to be
Speaker 12: there to decide whether to indict or not indict. And I think the Mueller investigation proves that special counsel are not consistent with our constitutional system and the rule of law.
Speaker 12: And I hope this case marks the end special counsel rather than new special counsel picked by Democrats to get Republicans, Republicans to get Democrats. I hope we're seeing an end to the special counsel, just like a few years ago we saw an end to the special prosecutor law.
Do you see
Speaker 13: any ethical quandary in commercial publishing outfits repurposing?
a
Speaker 13: public governmental document and then selling it on the market again i'm not saying it's straightforwardly unethical or anything like that but it has occurred to me
Speaker 14: that there's a little weirdness there
it's done all the
Speaker 15: time and it's part of the marketplace of ideas uh you can go online and get it for free and people should do that but if people want to read my introduction
Speaker 15: They have to pay, what, I don't know, $8 or something like
Speaker 11: that to get my version of it or the Washington Post version or the other versions. That happens repeatedly.
Speaker 12: The Star Report, the same thing. I did an introduction to the Star Report years ago. Many, many reports by the government have been commercially produced.
Speaker 16: Obviously, the Warren Commission Report, many others. So it's part of American free market society. You can publish for profit.
Speaker 16: Anything that the government publishes, the government has no copyright or trademark on anything they publish.
Fair
Speaker 17: enough. So you've published a book last year in which you made the case against
Speaker 13: impeachment. And I'm just curious, as a thought exercise, what could you come up with as the steel man case for impeachments, which is to say the most persuasive possible case that could be available to Democrats, even
Speaker 18: if you don't yourself have?
Speaker 18: agree with it? It's
a
Speaker 16: fair question. I would look for,
there are
Speaker 16: two precedents. One is Richard Nixon. And if you can find anything that's parallel to what Richard Nixon did, those are grounds for
Speaker 19: impeachment. Richard Nixon paid hush money to witnesses who might have testified in federal
cases.
Speaker 8: Against him, he told his subordinates to lie.
and
Speaker 8: he destroyed evidence. If Trump did any of those things, it
Speaker 16: would be an obstruction of justice. And obstruction of justice is a high crime and misdemeanor if committed while in office.
So I
Speaker 16: do believe that if they could come up with hard evidence of obstruction of
Speaker 12: justice, that would be an impeachable offense. The other precedent is George H.W. Bush.
He
Speaker 12: pardon Casper Weinberger and a handful of other people on
Speaker 16: the eve of their trial in order to stop the investigation of Iran-Contra by the special prosecutor in that case. And the special prosecutor said he did it to stop the investigation. And yet nobody suggested or implied or even thought about charging President Bush with obstruction of justice because you can't charge a
Speaker 11: president
Speaker 11: with obstruction for simply engaging in constitutionally protected activities under Article 2. And those activities include pardoning. They also include firing. So to the extent Mueller in his report suggested that you could indict a president for obstruction of justice for firing the head of the FBI or for firing Mueller if he had done that, they're just wrong as a matter of constitutional law.
Speaker 11: So, those are the two
Speaker 12: precedents, Nixon and Bush, and I think this case comes a lot closer to Bush than it does to Nixon. Ken
Starr did
Speaker 20: accuse Bill Clinton of witness
Speaker 21: tampering and other obstructive acts, so why would that not also serve as a precedent? Well,
he
Speaker 9: didn't indict him. All
Speaker 10: he did is charge him and refer 11 counts, I think it was, to the House of Representatives for impeachment, which they then did.
It
Speaker 11: backfired, but Starr saw his mission as not charging the president, but instead giving a roadmap to Congress to impeach. And that's what they did. And he did find crimes. And he found crimes committed, he said, by the president while
he was
Speaker 11: president. But again, according to at least Mueller, the constitution would forbid indicting or prosecuting a president while as an officer wouldn't prevent
it.
Speaker 11: indicting and prosecuting a president after he leaves
Speaker 22: office, either by way of impeachment or by being defeated for re-election or after his term is over. Of course,
after his
Speaker 22: second term is over, the statute of limitations would probably have expired on most of the alleged crimes. So
in this
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): column that you published at The Hill, your perhaps most vociferous reaction is
Speaker 5: prompted by this bizarre statement from Mueller, quote,
Speaker 5: If we had confidence that the president clearly did not commit a crime, we would have said so. And when I heard that, I had to double check and read the transcript because I almost couldn't believe what I was hearing. Because I've never I don't think
Speaker 24: I've ever heard more wildly fallacious reasoning from a prosecutor. Me
too, especially a
Speaker 15: prosecutor who was aware that everybody in the country virtually attacked Comey for doing essentially the same thing. Comey
Speaker 11: said, I'm not going to indict Hillary Clinton, but I'm going to criticize her for extreme carelessness. and everybody
Speaker 16: said that
Speaker 16: was wrong. The prosecutor should never go beyond saying, I'm not going to indict. And here you have this special counsel
Speaker 25: going well beyond it and implying that he might be guilty. And then in subsequent paragraphs, he says he implies that maybe he would have indicted him had it not been for the Justice Department rule in the constitutional
Speaker 16: prohibition against indicting or charging or prosecuting a sitting president. So he certainly put his thumb, as I put it in my column yesterday,
Speaker 16: his elbow on the scale in favor of impeaching President Trump, which is, I
Speaker 26: think, not the proper role of a prosecutor, whether he be a special counsel or an ordinary prosecutor. In
essence,
Speaker 17: what Mueller is asserting is that he views it as the proper remit of a prosecutor to
Speaker 27: not prove a crime, but to prove the absence of a crime. How is that possibly a workable standard?
It's
Speaker 10: not, obviously. And our burden of proof, unlike in the Soviet Union, where everything you did was a crime, unless there's a specific statute that says that what you did is legal, everything is illegal, except if it's statutorily legal. In the United States, we have the opposite rule.
Speaker 16: You're innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt. We have a strong presumption of innocence. And he did two things. One, he reversed the presumption of innocence. but second, he suggests
that
Speaker 16: that it's the role of the prosecutor to decide whether people are guilty or innocent. It's not. Prosecutors only decide whether there's sufficient evidence to meet the probable cause standard for bringing a person to trial. It's the trial itself which determines guilt or innocence based on cross-examination, zealous defense, exculpatory evidence, Brady evidence, a whole range of issues and proof beyond a reasonable doubt. And so he confused his role
with that
Speaker 16: of fact finder. He also did it
When
Speaker 16: he talked about the indictment against the Russians who can never be brought to
Speaker 28: trial, he described the indictment as if it were a conviction and as if the allegations in the indictment should be taken as true. We don't know whether they're true or not. I suspect
Speaker 16: they are. But the rule of law doesn't permit a prosecutor to say that this indictment proves anything. It
Speaker 29: doesn't prove anything. An indictment is simply a charging instrument, not evidence
of guilt.
Speaker 13: Mueller's statement seems to be a continuation of this trend.
Speaker 13: Where prosecutors, despite not bringing charges against political figures, seem entitled to go out in public and pronounce on the conduct of those figures. So you mentioned Comey as an example. There was another example, actually, in 2017 when Bill de Blasio, the mayor of New York City and current presidential candidate, was under federal and state investigations. And both state and federal prosecutors collaborated to...
opine
Speaker 13: on de Blasio's conduct while not bringing charges they said that they were hamstrung by the supreme court case that vacated the conviction of bob mcdonald but is this is this just a trend that pertains to high profile political figures or should we be concerned that it actually is more pervasive and could impinge on people of less stature
Speaker 30: Well, we should be concerned. Going after celebrities in this way goes back a long time. I was Mia Farrow's lawyer when she and Woody Allen went after each
Speaker 31: other. And you may remember that the state attorney in Connecticut reviewed all the evidence against Woody Allen and came to the
Speaker 32: conclusion that there was insufficient evidence to prosecute him for any improper conduct in relation to Mia Farrow's daughter. Nonetheless, he went out of his way to
Speaker 33: suggest...
Speaker 33: maybe there was some possibility that he might be guilty and that was a mistake back then so I think we've seen this
Speaker 34: violation of prosecutorial norms over many years most particularly when it comes to high-profile people but I think it's probably
Speaker 25: happening as well when it comes to ordinary folks and we have to put a stop to it
Speaker 25: Because prosecutors are in a position, are not in a position to opine on guilt or innocence because they don't hear exculpatory evidence. Their witnesses are not cross-examined. Their credibility is not challenged. There is no opportunity to see
Speaker 31: Brady information or other information that may prove exculpatory. So that's why we have trials. Prosecutors are not challenged.
Speaker 31: the trial you know the jury and judge and executioner they are just the prosecutors and they have no more credibility
Speaker 25: than a defense attorney does when a defense attorney gets up in court and says not guilty so you have a prosecutor getting up and saying
Speaker 31: the sufficient evidence to prosecute the defense attorney says not guilty we shouldn't believe either of them we should say let's wait and see let's hear a trial let's hear the evidence and then we can decide and a jury and a judge should decide
Speaker 31: whether or not the subject of the
Speaker 35: investigation is guilty or not guilty i think we're moving away from that i think the me too movement has moved
Speaker 25: away from that
if a
Speaker 25: person is charged under the me too movement that person is presumed guilty
Speaker 33: no matter what the evidence is i wrote an article in the wall street journal some time ago demanding that i be investigated by the fbi because i was falsely charged by a woman i never met never saw never heard of
And
Speaker 33: the only way to prove my innocence was to have an FBI investigation of me and her. And so I've spoken to the FBI about that and sought an investigation. The only way to completely
Speaker 36: prove my innocence, because in the Me Too movement, the presumption of innocence has been reversed if you're accused, you're guilty.
This is a
Speaker 13: slight tangent, but since you brought up the MeToo movement, I noticed that you signed a letter in defense of your colleague at Harvard Law, Ronald Sullivan, who ended up being ousted as a faculty dean by students who were upset that he was serving as
Speaker 37: defense counsel for Harvey Weinstein, the paradigmatic case
in the
Speaker 37: MeToo era. What is your reaction to his ouster, and
Speaker 38: what does it say about Harvard institutionally?
Well,
Speaker 39: you said he was ousted by the students. He was not. He was ousted by the dean of Harvard College. Right, in response
Speaker 33: to student pressure. Third high-ranking person at Harvard University. It was an outrage, an absolute outrage. It goes back to the McCarthy period. You know, if students can get a dean fired saying they feel unsafe in the
Speaker 40: presence of a lawyer—
The
Speaker 40: next person could say, I feel unsafe in the presence of a Republican. I feel unsafe in the presence of a Jew. I feel unsafe in the presence of a Muslim. I feel unsafe in the presence of a Red Sox fan or a Yankee fan. I mean, this is the new mantra
Speaker 41: of the new McCarthyism. I feel unsafe. First of all, it's a lie. These students don't feel unsafe. They are lying. If they said
it
Speaker 34: under oath, they'd go to jail for perjury.
Speaker 41: They are
Speaker 42: lying through their teeth. They don't feel unsafe.
Speaker 42: They just mouth those words because they know those words will
Speaker 31: result in them getting their way. And the university should never have given in to these students. In fact, I think the students should probably be disciplined for lying and saying they
Speaker 42: feel unsafe. They didn't feel unsafe when Ron Sullivan was defending a double murderer who had been convicted of murder.
Speaker 42: They didn't feel unsafe when he
Speaker 34: defended other people charged with horrible, horrible crimes. And they feel unsafe when he's defending Harvey Weinstein. It's just a lie.
And any
Speaker 34: dean who believes that nonsense
Speaker 40: should not be holding the position as dean. The dean should have used this occasion as an educational moment to teach students about the need for representation about John
Speaker 34: Adams.
and
Speaker 34: how he represented the people who were accused of the Boston Massacre. If these students had their way, John Adams wouldn't have been allowed to write the Declaration of Independence,
and he
Speaker 34: wouldn't have been allowed to run for president of the United States. These students have to learn something about due process and constitutional law. These are the same students who don't want free speech on campus except free speech for me, but not for thee. They don't want due process, only due process for me, but not for thee.
One
Speaker 34: of the things
Speaker 31: I regret about having you retire from Harvard five years ago is I'm not there to fight the good fight against these repressive, they call themselves progressive,
Speaker 25: repressive Stalinists who want to have it their way, who want to end free speech and due process
Speaker 40: and think they have a monopoly on truth with a capital T. Well, they don't. A university is a place to learn. A university is a place to hear all sides of an issue. And professors
Speaker 43: of law should be out there representing the most despised and unpopular criminals because they
Speaker 35: haven't.
Speaker 35: tenure. And that's what I did for my 50 years at Harvard. I took the most unpopular cases because I knew, at least I thought back then, I couldn't be fired. Who knows today whether I could still represent despised criminals, whether it be O.J. Simpson or Klaus von
Bülow or
Speaker 35: other people like that, and still maintain my job. Harvard should be ashamed of itself for what it did. And it's the leading university in the country. And when it does something like that, it establishes
Speaker 44: a precedent that will be followed by other universities, and it will hurt due process
Speaker 44: the rule of law and the
Speaker 45: constitutional right of counsel.
Speaker 20: - Right, I didn't mean to suggest that the students themselves literally ousted Sullivan. - No, of course. -
I just
Speaker 20: said that the administrators capitulated to the students' demands. - Exactly, right. - And actually your colleague Randall Kennedy wrote a column in the New York Times a few weeks ago where he said that this was the biggest embarrassment he's ever witnessed over the course of his decades at Harvard,
Speaker 13: obviously he's a friend of Sullivan's.
Speaker 13: But he made the same point about you, David. I mean, what's to stop students from claiming that they're unsafe if they're a Catholic and they have an atheist
Speaker 47: faculty dean? Right. No,
Speaker 48: no, of course. Look, I wrote a piece the day before Randy did. We basically made the same points, and I
Speaker 40: commend him for having written it. I will continue to write about this and rail against Harvard.
Speaker 40: for having done this. I hope Harvard reconsiders and reappoints him as dean. Only that way could they undo the
Speaker 19: harm that they've done. So I'm in complete sync with Randy Kenney and what he said.
Speaker 49: Okay, back to Mueller. One thing that also got my attention in Mueller's statement was that he
Speaker 13: declared it, quote, unconstitutional.
For the
Speaker 13: president to be charged with a crime while the president is in office that was muller opining that it would have been unconstitutional For him to charge trump with crimes and therefore he viewed it as
Speaker 49: not an option to do so, but that's not settled law That's the product of one office of legal counsel memo That is sitting somewhere in the Justice Department, which has never been tested in the courts
and
Speaker 49: In which another of your colleagues
Speaker 13: at Harvard, Andrew Crespo, wrote a long essay in 2017 for Lawfare, arguing that that memo was in fact not binding on
Speaker 24: Mueller. So that seems like yet another cop-out on Mueller's part.
Well, I think
Speaker 50: Mueller was right in the end. I think the Constitution does prevent a president from being indicted or prosecuted.
or
Speaker 51: prosecuted. If you look at the structure of the Constitution and the words of the Constitution, it suggests that a president can be prosecuted after he
Speaker 31: is impeached and removed from office.
So I
Speaker 31: think the better constitutional argument is in favor of what Mueller said,
Speaker 43: but you're right, it's not settled law. And the Justice Department Office of Legal Counsel is advisory and could be changed tomorrow. I do think it's binding on the special counsel. I think when
Speaker 22: the special counsel operates within the Justice Department, he or she
Speaker 22: is bound by the rules of the Justice Department. You don't get more power since you're appointed by the Justice Department to operate a special counsel
Speaker 43: than you would have if you were a line prosecutor. So I disagree with my colleague on that, but I do think it's not a settled issue and I do think Mueller used it as he
Speaker 41: apparently told Barth
Speaker 41: Twice I'm informed, and it's been reported, that his decision not to suggest prosecuting the president for obstruction was not at all influenced by his being precluded from charging him
Speaker 51: with a crime. That he did that on independent grounds. But now apparently he's either changed his mind or decided to use that as a justification or
Speaker 43: excuse. I don't think this was Mueller's finest hour.
Speaker 43: I think Mueller's finest hours were when he was completely silent and
Speaker 32: quiet. Every time he speaks, whether through the report or independently, I think he diminishes his credibility. He diminished his credibility by refusing to come to a firm conclusion
Speaker 52: about obstruction in the report. And then he diminished his credibility by going beyond the scope.
Speaker 52: what he's entitled to say when he said that if there had been clear evidence of innocence he would have said so
help me
Speaker 49: understand the logic here because if muller is claiming and you also agree
Speaker 13: that he would have been prohibited from bringing charges how could he then have reached a conclusion about the prosecutor prosecutability of any given charge
No, I
Speaker 48: think you can do that. I don't think that's logically inconsistent. You can say that had he not been the
Speaker 51: president, he would have committed acts that constitute a crime. But my question really is the one I posed earlier.
If a
Speaker 51: special counsel has no
Speaker 52: jurisdiction to prosecute a sitting president...
Speaker 52: what role does he have? Prosecutors
Speaker 53: are only supposed to decide whether or not to prosecute. And if that's off the table, why did we have a special prosecutor? Why didn't we instead have an independent,
Speaker 31: objective, nonpartisan commission to assess and evaluate all the evidence, produce a public report, hear all sides of the issue in public, and provide information how to prevent this in the future? That's what should have happened.
I
Speaker 31: called for that from
Speaker 44: day one. The appointment of a special counsel in this case was a fundamental mistake. I hope it's never repeated. I would like to see
Speaker 25: Congress pass legislation prohibiting the Justice Department from appointing special counsel. And if they do appoint special counsel, prohibiting
Speaker 43: special counsel from issuing public reports if they don't indict. If they do indict, also not issuing special reports.
I
Speaker 22: think the whole situation is inconsistent with the rule of law and our constitutional system.
Another
Speaker 54: comment Mueller made struck me as quite arrogant, and tell me if you agree. He said, quote, the
Speaker 5: report is my testimony, essentially implying that he
Speaker 37: desired not to testify before Congress. Well, it's not up to him whether he testified before Congress, and perhaps members of Congress, whether Republican or Democrat, have additional queries.
Speaker 37: For him, that would go beyond whatever is contained in the report. So I thought it was almost hubris on his part to insist that he's somehow above the processes of congressional inquiry. Well,
he's not
Speaker 55: quite clearly reminds me of a story in the Talmud about
Speaker 43: rabbis asking God what he meant by a certain thing in the Bible. And God said, I meant what I said. That's it.
Speaker 43: I'm not going to say anything further. That's God. Okay. Mueller is not God. And obviously no one is above the law and he has the obligation to respond to a congressional subpoena. Now he
Speaker 32: can refuse to answer questions based on privileges that prosecutors may have, but those privileges,
Speaker 51: for example,
would include not
Speaker 51: expressing a personal view about guilt or innocence for somebody that they decided not to prosecute. He's already
Speaker 43: waived that.
Speaker 43: when he made that statement yesterday. So I do think it showed a degree of arrogance. I hope he will be called. I hope he'll be asked several questions. One, why did he not
Speaker 56: come to any conclusion when it came to obstruction? Two, what he meant by that statement? Why did he put his thumb or his elbow on the
Speaker 53: scale when it
came to
Speaker 53: obstruction of justice? And I think three,
why he
Speaker 53: What was the criteria for hiring people to work on this investigation? I mean, I don't know
Speaker 43: the truth of this, but I hear from published reports that several of the people who were hired were very strong Clinton supporters. One
Speaker 57: went to
a party
Speaker 57: to celebrate Clinton's victory. By the way, I had a party in my house to celebrate Clinton's victory. It ended sadly, but I wasn't a prosecutor.
Speaker 20: Jeannie Reed, one of the lead prosecutors, represented Hillary Clinton in a lawsuit pertaining to her private email server.
I
Speaker 53: would think that that would be
Speaker 58: a disqualifying factor, and I would think that Mueller could be
Speaker 43: asked why he wasn't more sensitive to political partisanship. I know what his answer will be. Oh, I hire just the best prosecutors. I can't ask him whether they're Democrats or
Speaker 51: Republicans. Well, you can try to bring about some balance if you want to have credibility of your report,
and just
Speaker 56: make sure you don't have people on the report who have expressed strong, strong partisan views.
Speaker 56: they you know Muller did
Speaker 50: fire several of the people I can't remember it was Muller I think it was Muller but I'm not positive it was Muller Muller fired Strzok and Page
Speaker 59: yeah yeah when he
Speaker 51: found out that they were so partisan and yet he kept other people who were it seems to me
Speaker 43: equally partisan although maybe they kept their partisanship a little bit more discreet than than Strzok and
Speaker 60: Page kept theirs my reaction when
Speaker 61: watching that statement yesterday
Speaker 13: was that
Speaker 13: Muller, in essence, was rendering a political statement and you seem to come to a similar conclusion in your piece because I don't see how the statement could be read in any other way than Muller encouraging, as explicitly as he can given the limitations of his position, the House to initiate impeachment proceedings. He said, "The Constitution
Speaker 5: requires a process other than the criminal justice system to formally accuse the
Speaker 51: President of wrongdoing. What other process is there but impeachment?"
Speaker 51: Absolutely. That's what he meant. And he, you know, I predicted before the Mueller report came out, I predicted
Speaker 43: this publicly. And of course, people criticized me for it. I said the report would be devastating in its content against Trump, but that it would not charge the president with any crimes and that it would provide a roadmap for impeachment in Congress. I think I was right about all three of those things. And I think I've been right from day one in my predictions.
Speaker 51: And I think the folks on CNN have been wrong about every prediction they've made.
Speaker 51: And I think people should be held accountable in the
Speaker 53: court of public opinion for predictions they make when they are pundits on television if their predictions turn out wrong. And they should be credited if the predictions turned out right. But we have no accountability
Speaker 62: for pundits on television.
Speaker 63: Right. So just an exercise. Do you think now...
Speaker 63: Now that
Speaker 64: there is an ineluctable march toward impeachment in the House, we have multiple chairmen of committees in the House endorsing impeachment just over the past 24 hours. Many of the big name presidential candidates endorse impeachment. My view is that we do seem to be heading intractably, at least toward the initiation
Speaker 65: of impeachment proceedings. And I don't know how Pelosi resists that for long.
Speaker 66: Well, I'm a liberal Democrat. I want to see the Democrats win.
Speaker 66: And as the
Speaker 7: result of that, I don't want to see them go down the rabbit hole of impeachment. That is a guarantee loser if they do that. Look, there's only one person running for president of the
Speaker 28: United States on the Democratic side now. And that's that's Biden, Joe Biden. Everybody else is just running for the Democratic nomination. They're not running for president. They're making statements that would preclude them from ever winning a national election.
But
Speaker 32: they just want to win the nomination. I think Biden is trying to actually become president. And if you want to win the nomination today as a Democrat, you have to show you're further left than
Speaker 35: everybody else. And that's a prescription for winning the nomination, but for losing the election.
And I
Speaker 67: think that's where the Democrats are heading these days.
Is it not
Speaker 64: feasible, though, that a protracted impeachment proceeding in which Trump's behavioral excesses are...
Put
Speaker 64: at the front of mind in the public consciousness and his potential criminality is discussed day after day. Isn't it possible that
Speaker 13: that could redound to his electoral disadvantage and perhaps even inflame and energize the Democratic Party's base? I know this is all speculative, but it does seem to me that Trump and Trump supporters and maybe
Speaker 64: even Trump himself are a little too overconfident about this somehow being a boon to him.
No,
Speaker 68: they shouldn't be overconfident. They should look to what happened in Israel, where you
Speaker 43: have Benjamin Atayahu, who is under investigation. And in the most recent election, his party got 35 seats and the opposition got 35 seats, though he had more
parties on
Speaker 43: his side of the right wing coalition than the other side. But he wasn't able to form a coalition. Now they're going to new elections and the new elections will take place just at about the same time that his hearing occurs as to whether
Speaker 44: he gets indicted.
Speaker 44: it or not. So it's always speculative when you have a leader. And I don't want to compare Trump and Netanyahu. They're very, very,
Speaker 32: very different people. And the allegations against them are very, very different. But that's the only analogy that comes to mind right now. And so I think you're right. It is speculative as to what impact an investigation, an impeachment investigation, would have on a general election.
Speaker 51: But I think that
If
Speaker 51: you look at Clinton, I think you see that in the end, Clinton's popularity
Speaker 69: numbers went up considerably after he was impeached, unsuccessfully. But Clinton
Speaker 70: was impeached after he was reelected. So there's a different set of
Speaker 43: circumstances. But his numbers went up anyway. I agree with you. Look, there's no and there's no comparison between the two kinds of cases. What Clinton was charged with was a low crime.
not
Speaker 43: a high crime. He was charged with a personal failure, but not something that impacted on his holding of office. Whereas, you
Speaker 56: know, the Trump investigation was directed at many things, including his own election, although the Mueller report concluded that there was no evidence of any improper
Speaker 71: collusion. And
there was no
Speaker 72: issue. I mean, there was no question of, you know, treason wasn't being bandied about as a term during the Clinton
Speaker 73: impeachment. So the Gravity now just seems different.
Speaker 73: Well,
the
Speaker 74: treason is a laughable offense as related to President Trump. You just have to read the Constitution. The
Speaker 43: Constitution, the only crime defined in the Constitution is treason, and it defines it with great specificity. And it's not even a close question as to whether anything alleged against the president would constitute treason. So that's just a metaphor
Speaker 44: that's being used.
Speaker 44: by people who haven't read the Constitution or who have read it and are purposely abusing its language for partisan political purposes.
Speaker 61: Are you supporting Joe Biden? Are you going to endorse a candidate in the Democratic?
Speaker 58: I'm going to wait. I'm going to wait. I like Joe Biden.
Speaker 56: I've known him for years and years. I first met him through Ted Kennedy, who I was a very close friend with and supporter of. And so I've known Joe
for a
Speaker 56: long, long, long time.
And
Speaker 56: I like him very much. I think he'd be a very strong candidate, but I'm not
Speaker 43: endorsing anybody at this point. I want to see what the field looks like. I want to see how it winnows down. And, you know, I hope I'll be able to support a liberal Democrat. Where I would have trouble
Speaker 44: is with a radical hard left Democrat. And
I hope
Speaker 44: the Democrats are smart enough not to nominate
a person
Speaker 41: like the three women who recently elected to Congress
to,
who
Speaker 41: could win in their small districts, but could never win in a statewide election and couldn't
Speaker 44: even win three states in a national election. The Democrats have made that mistake in the past when they nominated some terrific, terrific
Speaker 32: candidates, Mike Dukakis, McGovern and Mondale.
And I
Speaker 32: think between the three of them, they won 10 states, if I'm not mistaken, something like that.
Speaker 44: Democrats cannot compete
Speaker 57: from the left.
And
Speaker 57: they have to compete from the center. And I think Joe Biden is as close to a centrist. I hope he doesn't blow
that by
Speaker 75: trying to move harder to the left in order to win the nomination. That would be a mistake.
I know you
Speaker 13: don't have much of an affinity ideologically with Bernie Sanders, but would it give you any contentment or
Speaker 54: happiness to see a major party nominate for the first time a Jewish candidate?
I
Speaker 58: would vote against
Speaker 43: him. I would campaign against him. I would contribute against him. I would do everything in my power to see him defeated for one reason. He
Speaker 25: has actively supported an anti-Semite,
Speaker 57: namely Jeremy Corbyn. He went over to campaign for Jeremy Corbyn. And anybody who campaigns or supports Jeremy Corbyn is not somebody who will ever, under any circumstances, get my vote.
But the fact of
Speaker 76: Sanders being Jewish wouldn't be a benefit?
In
Speaker 76: your mind, or is that an identity-based
Speaker 78: thing that you're not interested in? I
would
Speaker 77: never vote for anybody based on their religion, ethnicity, race, or gender. And I would
Speaker 44: hate to see the first Jewish candidate for president be somebody who supports
Speaker 52: British anti-Semitism. That would really put new meaning to self-hating Jew. I would much prefer to see a Muslim, a Christian, an atheist, anybody else
Speaker 52: other than a Jew like Sanders, who is willing to support somebody like Corbyn.
Speaker 43: Look, I grew up with Bernie Sanders and many people like him in Brooklyn. And they were all a bunch of red diaper babies who really saw the glory of communism and the hard left
Speaker 31: and socialism. And then what does Bernie Sanders do? He wants to bring about racial equality in America. So he moves to Vermont, the least racially integrated
Speaker 33: state in the entire United States.
Speaker 33: and operates out of there. So I have very little good to
Speaker 43: say about Sanders. I think he hurt terribly the Clinton nomination. I think Clinton might very well be president if
Speaker 57: not for Bernie Sanders today.
So don't
Speaker 57: ask me to say anything nice about Bernie Sanders. Look, I'm not going to say anything nice about Noam Chomsky just because
Speaker 43: he's Jewish.
Or
Speaker 43: Norman Finkelstein, because he's Jewish. So don't expect me to say anything nice about Bernie Sanders, because he was born to a Jewish
Speaker 44: family. I just don't respect him. I don't admire him. And I don't support his politics. And I despise his going over.
Speaker 25: And supporting Jeremy Corbyn, who was the most anti-Semitic person in the world
Speaker 35: today in public life, in the Western world today in public life, who has a chance of becoming the prime
Speaker 43: minister of America's greatest ally. That would be such a disaster for the Jewish people, such a disaster for Israel, that anybody like Sanders who helps that happen is
Speaker 79: somebody who has to count me as an enemy.
Okay,
Speaker 20: well, for the record, I strongly disagree with your portrayal of Corbyn and Sanders, but that's a different subject. We can
Speaker 80: have another podcast on that. Yeah, that
Speaker 37: would be fascinating, actually. And I know you have to go, but just one final question. There was a report in the New York Times, or rather an interview with Michael Wolff in the New York Times today, where he's publishing a new book. He seems to be something fabulous, and he claims in the book…
Speaker 37: That you were offered a massive or you demanded a retainer from President Trump to provide him with legal services like is and you
Speaker 5: denied that as being true. What could have possibly been the basis for that claim as far as you can tell?
Speaker 44: Well, I first heard that false statement from David Boyce, a lawyer in New York.
Speaker 44: who apparently was telling people that it's totally false, totally categorically false. In fact, I've
Speaker 82: just written to my lawyers, seeing whether it's defamatory. And if it is defamatory, I fully intend to sue Wolf. He never checked with me. He never asked me. He can't possibly have a source for that because it never happened. I never, ever had a conversation with President Trump.
Speaker 82: involving retainers involving official legal representation nothing like that i made my position clear from the very beginning i am not a trump supporter i want to defend as an independent person trump's civil liberties the way i defend everybody else's civil liberties and the idea that i would ask for a million dollar retainer to represent Donald Trump is just
Speaker 35: preposterous it's a lie it's a made-up story
And
Speaker 35: if that's the level of credibility of this book, nobody should believe a single word in it. And as I say, I've contacted my lawyers to see if the statement itself
Speaker 57: is defamatory. And if it is, I will sue him and he will not be able to defend it because there can't be a source for a statement that never happened.
To be clear, did
Speaker 37: you offer to provide legal services to Trump through any kind of intermediary?
Speaker 83: Absolutely not. Absolutely not. Never under any circumstances. Period. Period.
Speaker 83: Without any equivocation,
Speaker 82: without anything other than absolutely
Speaker 83: no. Absolutely no.
Okay, well. And I
Speaker 38: never asked for any kind of a retainer. It's just totally false. Okay, well, we shall see how that plays out. I know you have to go. It
Speaker 85: may play out
Speaker 25: in court.
I
Speaker 25: would expect that Wolf would withdraw it. I would challenge him to name a
Speaker 82: source or to even state that he has a source because he couldn't possibly have a source for this. He describes a dinner meeting at which the dinner meeting
Speaker 35: is correct. I was invited to the White House to talk about the Middle
Speaker 57: East peace plan. I went, had dinner with the president and a handful of other people. Those are the only people who are at the meeting, and I'm sure they will all
Speaker 86: swear on the road that no such conversation ever occurred.
Speaker 87: okay well uh thank you again for spending some time you have to go
Speaker 54: um and maybe we'll do it again at a later date sure thanks be well all right thanks bye
okay there you have it your
Speaker 3: feedback as always
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): is valued also valued would be your contributions via paypal or patreon links are in the description box if you're watching this on youtube
or
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): If you're listening to the podcast, you can find it easily by clicking on the Patreon link. And
remember to
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): subscribe on YouTube, subscribe to the podcast through iTunes or Stitcher, and I will talk to you later.